<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal Insights on Amir Kiani&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/personal-insights/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Personal Insights on Amir Kiani&#39;s Blog</description>
    <image>
      <title>Amir Kiani&#39;s Blog</title>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.139.0</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/personal-insights/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>No Elevation Here - A Review of Robert Glazer’s ‘Elevate’</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/no-elevation-here---a-review-of-robert-glazers-elevate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/no-elevation-here---a-review-of-robert-glazers-elevate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t remember exactly how this book entered my to-read shelf. One day, I found it on sale on the Kindle Store and bought it without checking the rating and reviews on Goodreads. I wish I had!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.robertglazer.com/&#34;&gt;Robert Glazer&lt;/a&gt; is an award-winning CEO and entrepreneur. His interviews in multiple podcasts and magazines piqued my interest, leading me to believe his book would be equally insightful. Unfortunately, like many self-help books written by successful leaders, I found &amp;ldquo;Elevate&amp;rdquo; lacking in novelty and inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I don&rsquo;t remember exactly how this book entered my to-read shelf. One day, I found it on sale on the Kindle Store and bought it without checking the rating and reviews on Goodreads. I wish I had!</p>
<p><a href="https://www.robertglazer.com/">Robert Glazer</a> is an award-winning CEO and entrepreneur. His interviews in multiple podcasts and magazines piqued my interest, leading me to believe his book would be equally insightful. Unfortunately, like many self-help books written by successful leaders, I found &ldquo;Elevate&rdquo; lacking in novelty and inspiration.</p>
<p>The book introduces a 4-principle framework for capacity building:</p>
<ul>
<li>Spiritual Capacity</li>
<li>Intellectual Capacity</li>
<li>Physical Capacity</li>
<li>Emotional Capacity</li>
</ul>
<p>Upon skimming through the book and seeing this list, I had a feeling of déjà vu. Apart from a few quotes from notable figures in capacity building and personal growth, I hardly ever felt the urge to highlight anything noteworthy.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a brief overview of some key points from the book:</p>
<h4 id="highlights">Highlights</h4>
<p><strong>Intro</strong></p>
<blockquote>
<p>For everyone who knows deep down they can be more.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This quote initially raised my expectations sky-high. I was ready to add Robert Glazer to my list of personal heroes. He begins with a story about his weekly newsletter, Friday Forward, and its unexpected success, hoping to hook readers for the chapters ahead.</p>
<p><strong>Chapter 1: What Is Capacity Building?</strong></p>
<p>Capacity building is defined as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The method by which individuals seek, acquire, and develop the skills and abilities to consistently perform at a higher level in pursuit of their innate potential.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Glazer emphasizes that capacity building is about doing more of the right things, not just more things. He introduces the four elements of capacity building:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Spiritual</strong> (understanding who you are)</li>
<li><strong>Intellectual</strong> (enhancing your ability to think and learn)</li>
<li><strong>Physical</strong> (improving your physical performance)</li>
<li><strong>Emotional</strong> (facing challenges and managing relationships)</li>
</ol>
<p>Glazer believes our growth is best when all four elements develop in tandem.</p>
<p><strong>Chapter 2: Build Your Spiritual Capacity</strong></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Don’t consider the word “Spiritual” as a religious term in the context of capacity building. It refers to understanding who you are and what you want most in life.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Core values serve as guideposts for navigating life, and understanding them is crucial for growth.</p>
<p><strong>Chapter 3: Build Your Intellectual Capacity</strong></p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Anyone who stops learning is old, whether at twenty or eighty. Anyone who keeps learning stays young.” —Henry Ford</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Intellectual capacity involves the ability to learn, plan, and execute with discipline. Improving this capacity starts with the belief that it can be improved.</p>
<p><strong>Chapter 4: Build Your Physical Capacity</strong></p>
<p>Glazer discusses the importance of a healthy body on overall life quality, emphasizing good nutrition and sleep.</p>
<p><strong>Chapter 5: Build Your Emotional Capacity</strong></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Think about a race car. If your spiritual, physical, and intellectual capacities are the tools to design, build, and improve the car, your emotional capacity is your ability to drive it amidst other drivers and unexpected obstacles.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He underscores the importance of challenging oneself, gratitude, and maintaining meaningful relationships.</p>
<p><strong>Chapter 6: Build A Better Path</strong></p>
<p>Nothing particularly noteworthy was found in this chapter.</p>
<p>Each chapter ends with an action plan for practical steps in capacity building. You might find these useful if you&rsquo;re curious about specific techniques.</p>
<h3 id="my-personal-conclusion">My Personal Conclusion:</h3>
<p>I gave this book a rating of 1 out of 5 because it failed to offer anything new or interesting. However, this might be due to my previous readings and high expectations from an author of Glazer&rsquo;s caliber.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Passion vs. Practicality - My Struggle Between Finance and Programming</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/passion-vs.-practicality---my-struggle-between-finance-and-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/passion-vs.-practicality---my-struggle-between-finance-and-programming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve reached the boiling point with the situation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an idiom we all use from time to time to express feelings of being overwhelmed, often accompanied by anxiety. However, what I&amp;rsquo;ve been experiencing over the last two days is much more intense. To describe it, I thought it might be fitting to draw on my long-forgotten days of studying chemical engineering. While many people think of the boiling point as the hottest state a substance can experience, every thermodynamics reference explains that the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Critical_point_(thermodynamics)&#34;&gt;critical point&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is what we should be looking for. This state is achieved by controlling both pressure and temperature, rendering the substance unidentifiable as a solid, liquid, or gas. In other words, it loses its distinct characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;I&rsquo;ve reached the boiling point with the situation.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This is an idiom we all use from time to time to express feelings of being overwhelmed, often accompanied by anxiety. However, what I&rsquo;ve been experiencing over the last two days is much more intense. To describe it, I thought it might be fitting to draw on my long-forgotten days of studying chemical engineering. While many people think of the boiling point as the hottest state a substance can experience, every thermodynamics reference explains that the <strong><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Critical_point_(thermodynamics)">critical point</a></strong> is what we should be looking for. This state is achieved by controlling both pressure and temperature, rendering the substance unidentifiable as a solid, liquid, or gas. In other words, it loses its distinct characteristics.</p>
<p>So, <strong>&ldquo;at my critical point&rdquo;</strong> has been my status for the last two days. I&rsquo;ve been thoroughly reviewing my educational and personal development path since graduating high school. To be honest, not only are the results not in my favor, but I also feel that nowhere along this journey have I felt satisfied, even briefly.</p>
<p>Everything traces back to when I was about twelve years old, and my father bought us a PC. I was fascinated by this new phenomenon, not for gaming, but for the potential it had to become anything I could imagine. Seeing my passion, my mom enrolled me in a professional course, which I didn&rsquo;t appreciate at the time. Later, I realized it was the MCSE Professional Certification Course by Microsoft. By the time I turned eighteen, my curiosity had given me a solid foundation in the digital world, making computer engineering my priority for undergraduate studies. But then, a turning point occurred: my parents got divorced. My role in the family shifted from needing support and guidance to acting as a mediator, solving problems beyond my mental capacity. Consequently, my priority changed from pursuing my passion to regaining peace of mind and focus.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I&rsquo;ll put the needle of the compass on the house and find the farthest place from home to live,&rdquo; I told my mom as I revised my university and major preferences.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://amirkiani.info/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/compass-224x300.jpg"></p>
<p>Three months later, I was a student in a major I knew nothing about, in a city near the southeast border of the country, which didn&rsquo;t even have proper drinking water. I lacked the courage, and had no truthful friend or mentor to tell me about the option of quitting. So, I stuck to the plan, and day by day, the snowball effect increasingly diverged my ideal path from the one I was on.</p>
<p>Eventually, I got a second chance. I thought changing my major for my master&rsquo;s might help, and due to <a href="https://amirkiani.info/about/">the experiences and achievements</a> during my bachelor&rsquo;s years, I chose an MBA. Again, I could have pursued my interests by selecting a computer-related field, but without anyone to encourage me, I watched my dreams slip away once more.</p>
<p>Now, I&rsquo;m twenty years old and at the end of <a href="https://amirkiani.info/about/">my MBA journey</a>. My interest and passion for computers and programming are stronger than ever. But I&rsquo;m unsure if it&rsquo;s wise to follow my heart for my last chance. The price could be a two-year compulsory military service to enter the job market officially, plus accepting that a decade of my life—the supposed best decade—is wasted and gone, and I must come to terms with this fact.</p>
<p>Feeling extremely overwhelmed this morning, I googled &ldquo;software developer vs financial analyst.&rdquo; The first result was <a href="https://medium.com/free-code-camp/why-i-learned-to-code-instead-of-pursuing-a-career-in-finance-d5ef437c6922">an outstanding article by an Iranian on the Medium blog of FreeCodeCamp.org</a>. It&rsquo;s rare to find a specific answer to a buried query, but this was one of those times.</p>
<p>As Amir explains, he has faced a similar dilemma. In a fair comparison, he might have experienced an even harder situation since his financial studies are more extensive than mine. Yet, he handled it perfectly, following his passion for programming before it was too late. I highly recommend everyone read the entire <a href="https://medium.com/free-code-camp/why-i-learned-to-code-instead-of-pursuing-a-career-in-finance-d5ef437c6922">article</a>. While it&rsquo;s about a finance student turning into a programmer, many people from different fields might resonate with the idea and the aspects discussed regarding programming.</p>
<p>Amir Ghafouri&rsquo;s contact info:</p>
<ul>
<li>Amir&rsquo;s Article on Medium: <a href="https://medium.com/free-code-camp/why-i-learned-to-code-instead-of-pursuing-a-career-in-finance-d5ef437c6922">Click Here</a></li>
</ul>
<p>I posted this on my blog firstly to promote Amir&rsquo;s amazing content and secondly as a self-reminder of my mistakes and a catalyst for better future steps.</p>
<p>Let me know your opinion on my story or share a related story of your own in the comments.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
